now joins in on the show to talk about
numbers as well thanks so much for
taking time out let's begin with Trends
in the motor segment this quarter would
you say that the growth is back or do
you see a little bit
guarded so if you look at it I think uh
in so far as uh motor is concerned uh
for us the uh trend line seems to be
very very encouraging uh for example in
quarter 1 our growth in motor was
roughly at about 5 % in Quarter Two that
number has kind of inched up to almost
close to about 10
11% uh and relative to the market I
think we have been able to substantially
narrow down the Gap in so far as growth
in that segment is concerned the reason
for us to be slightly still growing
lower than the market is if you look at
the combined ratio which is the results
of what we underwrite for the industry
motor combined ratio still continues to
remain elevated upwards of 120% plus uh
so hence to that extent uh is where we
are still kind of taking a guarded
stance having said that I think the
trend line seems to be looking very very
encouraging and more importantly I think
we will obviously also wait for the rest
of the year in terms of how the expense
of management plays play play out for
many players in the market because uh
that's something if you look at for
roughly half of the industry
participants are having their expense of
management in excess of the regulatory
thresholds for is Lombard where we are
well well within the threshold and H to
that extent as and when that starts to
see getting corrected we would obviously
be able to see incremental opportunities
so you you have increased pricing has
the competition increased pricing
especially in the motor segment as
well so I think again if you look at it
uh uh motor a segment uh uh for ICC
Lombard towards the beginning of the
calendar year is when we had started to
affect small amount of price increases
these are single digit price increases
that we have seen and as I said many
players in the market were very
aggressive over the last 18 to 24 months
uh many of them have started to
calibrate uh their growth numbers uh
given the I higher levels of combined
ratio that I spoke about of roughly in
excess of 120% for the market and that's
something that is not sustainable so
hence many midsized relatively large
sized as well as small companies they
all have kind of started to calibrate
growth which is definitely very very
positive from an overall Market
development standpoint uh at an industry
level I would not necessarily say that
uh people have taken price changes but
we do see instances of uh companies
calibrating growth either by increasing
small amount of pricing or more
importantly as I said also to kind of
look at the overall expense of
management so how do you see uh the loss
ratio playing out and how comfort
comfortable are you on the
risk I think from an is Lombard
standpoint one of the biggest strength
that we have is our ability to slice and
dice portfolio in terms of various risk
segments and that's the basis on which
we have always balanced growth with
profitability and hence to that extent
even when you look at motor uh of course
what we keep saying is to definitely
refrain from looking at quarter to
quarter numbers because there could be a
lot of elements that could go into uh
quarterly outcomes rather a better thing
will be to look at more yearly uh
numbers in terms of the way how the loss
ratio trend lines could play out uh
specifically in the context of the motor
line of business for let's say it has
got two components motor own damage and
motor third party on own damage I think
the loss ratio range that we are
comfortable in terms of underwriting is
between 65 to 70% and similarly third
party again if you look at the full year
numbers that broadly has been operating
at the range of 70% or there about so
again that's a range that we would be
comfortable in terms of uh underwriting
and disis selecting portfolio segments
but having said that we would again not
look at just one of the components of
underwriting which is in terms of the
loss experience we would obviously want
to look at it more in terms of the
overall combined ratio for the segment
and for the company as a whole which is
where we have again talked to the market
to possibly get down to the objective of
combine that we have laid out by end of
next year which is by end of 25 we would
want to see our combin ratio for the
company as a whole going down to
102% you know also wanted to understand
about how the two wheeler segment has
been shaping up because last time we
spoke you said that it was doing better
directionally is it now looking
substantially
better so two wheer again for Isis alard
has been our inherent for uh and that's
where roughly one in four two wheeler
insurances that happen in the market is
predominantly insured by IC Lombard and
hence to that extent that segment is
something if you look at from an overall
premium contribution uh out of the
overall motor line of business two wheer
for us contributes roughly about 27 28%
of the overall mix and that's broadly uh
being the levels at which uh we have
seen the mix of two wheer getting
contributed if you look at in terms of
market demand while on the private car
side the demand seems to have largely
come back two wheeler at least I'm when
you also talk to the oems and in general
when you train to fight and when we also
do our own uh let's say Channel checks
clearly we see that still things are not
necessarily out of the woods in so far
as two wheer demand is concerned
possibly it will take maybe another
couple of quarters for things to come
back having said that as I said for us
two wheer in inherently has been our
Forte and hence we continue to drive
growth to that through that particular
Subs segment of the M business sure
gopal tell us what's happening with the
health segment as as well because growth
has been good this quarter but going
forward what is the expectation from
both individual as well as group
segments if you look at uh in terms of
what I had spoken even last quarter uh
for us both corporate health and let's
say individual or retail Health both of
them are preferred segments of
opportunities and on both the segments
we have had industry beating numbers uh
for example uh on retail or individual
health uh we grew by almost about close
to 19 20% whether you look at quarter
two or half year numbers the industry
growth has been closer to about 18 19%
or thereabout so clearly we have been
able to uh beat the industry numbers
when it comes to individual or retail
health and that's an area if you
recollect we have been talking about
making continued investments in building
our distribution Force which
predominantly happens through the uh
agency distribution and that number if
you look at it for Quarter Two the
retail health agency growth has been
upwards of 21% or that about so we are
very very excited with the way how the
distribution Investments are playing out
on the retail Health franchise expansion
and because of which we have been able
to grow faster than the market our
market share has SL slightly inched up
we used to be less than 3% market share
in retail Health inity now that market
share is slightly upwards to 3.1% or
thereabout but having said that I think
as I said we have been able to grow
faster than the market on the uh retail
Health front on corporate health I think
the outcome is pretty much the same
uh again we have been able to kind of
beat the industry in so far as the
overall growth percentages are concerned
the good news is uh it has been across
the board uh increase that that one has
seen when I say across the board it has
been a growth that has been contributed
by increase in volumes it has been a
growth contributed by increase in price
and equally it has been a growth that it
has been contributed by a creation of
market share so it's an all around kind
of an increase that one has seen on the
corporate Health side
now your loss ratio on health continues
to rise are there any concerns with
respect to that where is it that you see
your loss ratio for the overall health
segment
stabilizing so again as we keep saying
again when you start looking at numbers
on a quarterly basis obviously it could
sometimes lead to let's say misleading
outcome primarily because what happens
is uh in quarter 2 is largely periods of
monsoon when you generally get to see
relatively higher incidences of Health
ailments and then to that extent you
will possibly see again this is not just
a quarter two phenomenon of this year in
general when you look at quarter two of
historical periods you will always find
the loss ratios to be slightly elevated
than the rest of the quarters which
tends to get normalized uh as we head
into the subsequent uh quarter three or
quarter four uh which is why again when
you look at it on a full year basis as I
said in so far as the underwriting of
this particular segment is concerned I
think we're very very comfortable with
the way we we are doing our underwriting
and risk selection the good news is uh
majority of the portfolio on the
corporate Health side is relatively mid
and small siiz corporate Health accounts
which ensures that we able to get a
reasonable price and more importantly we
are also able to kind of retain the
accounts for a very very long period of
times uh and hence to that EXT to answer
your point I think we are quite
comfortable with the loss ratio range
which we have generally spoken to again
to the market to be around that uh 94
95% levels because here inherently the
loss ratios will stay elevated but the
relative cost of acquiring this business
is a low single- digit number which is
why on balance I think again from a
combined ratio perspective it fits
within our objective and hence uh we
don't see any challenges in so far as
writing the segment is
concerned okay and you also have spoken
about how your expenses of management
are likely to change the game this year
and still despite that last quarter you
suggested that two-thirds of insurers
don't actually meet the eom guidelines
so tell us a little bit more what is
actually happening at the ground level
what kind of traction that is it that
you expect the regulator to take or what
kind of action are you expecting in case
of non-compliance of
eom so I think again uh again when you
look at public numbers uh so that
two-thirds of the company was for the
last Financial year now we have uh uh
the quarter one numbers for the players
in the market uh the Tren the trend
seems to be kind of largely similar
which is more than half of the industry
participants are operating at an expense
of management threshold which I said is
well above the threshold of either 30 or
35% as the case may be um I think in so
far as the regulatory action is
concerned again if you look at the eom
guidelines the regulator had G given
them a Glide path for companies which
are above the threshold to meet the E
guidelines within those stated Glide
path but having said that uh it's been
just couple of we will have to wait and
see how quarter 2 numbers play out for
most players in the market but the
regulator will obviously wait and
possibly see the trend line over the
next uh one or two more quarters and
possibly see at the end of the year in
terms of how many companies are still
operating at thresholds which are over
and above the laid down eom threshold
and I'm sure uh given the given the
thought process with which the regulator
has come out with these guidelines they
would obviously start taking possibly
severe steps against companies which are
continuing to operate at levels which
are higher higher than the laid down
guidelines now let's talk about uh the
change of God there bav Das Gupta who
has speed the company for nearly 15
years moves on what
changes for from an i Lombard standpoint
for us management succession is
something that we actively engage in uh
not just now not the fact that barov
term was coming to an end but even
otherwise at a management level
succession is something that the board
and the NRC actively engages in and
hence to that extent whenever any of
these situations entail then to that
extent there is enough and more
leadership depth that we have both
within the company and within icsa group
and in this particular instance I think
the good part is I think the NRC and the
board found sanjie uh who has been a
part and parcel of icsi group and with
IC Lombard since 2015 uh sping the
retail division he he is the one who
would now take charge as the MD and CEO
so hence to that extent I think it has
been extremely smooth transition and it
indicates the leadership depth that the
institution has created over a period of
time and hence to that extent the
transition is very very seamless and in
so far as the uh objective of the way
how things will get played out I think
it will start I Lombard has always been
kind of driving growth with profits and
even with this leadership change the
larger underwriting philosophy of the
thought process in the way of the
businesses will be underwritten will
continue to remain the same and H to
answer your point I think it has been a
very very similar
transition all right thanks uh gopal
really appreciate your time